Guide to the Paul Burns Photograph Collection ALBA.PHOTO.184
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Paul Burns Photographs
1937-1938, (Bulk 1937)
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Burns, Paul, 1906?-1996
ALBA.PHOTO.184
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Paul Burns ([1906?]-1996) was a writer, teacher, and Writers Union activist. In 1937, Burns went to Spain as a volunteer and rose to the rank of Company Commander. The images in this collection were accrued by Burns in the course of his work as a Commander in Spain. The collection contains group photographs and portraits of members of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, Spanish soldiers and scouts and other international volunteers including Cubans and Yugoslavs.
Provenance
The Paul Burns Photograph Collection was donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives, formerly housed at Brandeis University, by Paul Burns in 1984. The collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Paul Burns ([1906?]-1996) was a writer, teacher, and Writers Union activist. Boston-born of Irish parentage, he worked his way through college and graduated from Middlebury College with an MA in Sociology. In 1937 he enlisted in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade to fight against Franco’s rebel forces in Spain. Burns was a sergeant in command of the Irish section and later became second in command of the infantry, Lincoln Battalion. He was active on the Jarama front and participated in two of the major campaigns of the war; the Battle of Madrid and the offensive at Brunete from July to August 1937. He was wounded twice—first, when shot in the arms and legs in Jarama on February 23, 1937 and again, in Brunete, when he was wounded by machine-gun fire. He left the International Brigades with a final rank of lieutenant.
Burns returned to the United States in October 1937 and was subsequently elected national commander of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. He wrote for the Daily Worker, Sunday, and Story Magazine. After settling in Chicago, he became associate editor of the Daily Record, working in his spare time on a book of stories about the Irish battalion of the Lincoln Brigade. He was also a correspondent for the United Nations. Burns died in 1996. He was 90 years old.
Scope and Content Note
The Paul Burns Photograph Collection includes 76 black and white photographs of varying sizes: 62 5.5 x 4 inch prints, six 8 x 10 inch prints, five 5 x 7 inch prints, one 4.5 x 3.5 inch print, one 4 x 3 inch print, and one 3.25 x 2.25 inch print. There is also one black and white negative that matches print number 184:1:1:27. The negative is contained in folder 27.
The bulk of the Paul Burns Photograph Collection consists of photographs Burns gathered during the course of his work as a commander in the International Brigades. The collection contains group photographs and portraits of members of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, Spanish soldiers and scouts and other international volunteers including Cubans and Yugoslavs.
When the collection was donated to ALBA, Burns provided a numbered inventory with captions, which corresponded to 63 prints. These photographs can be found in Series I. The remaining 13 prints are arranged by subject.
Among the individuals pictured are Jack Bjoze, Harry Fisher, Oliver Law, Steve Nelson, Douglas Roach, Jack Shirai, and Vladimir Copi'c.
Series I: The 63 prints in the series are arranged according to Burns' original numbering scheme. Burns provided typed captions, which are filed with the prints in each folder. Includes black and white photographs taken in Spain during the Civil War. In the captions, Burns' original writing and syntax have been preserved. In a few cases the spelling of names has been corrected. Approximately three-quarters are group shots of volunteers-primarily American-but also Cubans, Germans (Thaelmann Brigade), Greeks, Irish, Scots, Welsh, and Yugoslavs. Of particular interest are the photos pertaining to the Tom Mooney Machine Gun Company and the Saklatvala Battalion. Tom Mooney was a trade unionist who, in 1937, was serving a life sentence in Alcatraz. The Saklatvala Battalion was the first British unit, which included Welsh, Scots, and Irish volunteers. It was named after Shapurji Saklatvala, a native of India and one of the first members of the Communist Party to become a British MP. The remainder include prints of daily life (cooking, washing, etc.), wall newspapers (public bulletin boards for the troops), a front-line barbershop, a court-martial proceeding, a concert behind enemy lines, and a grave of a member of the Saklatvala Battalion.
Series II: The 13 prints are arranged alphabetically by topic. Includes black and white group shots (identified and unidentified) taken in Spain during the Civil War, a portrait of Douglas Roach and John Perrone in Spain, a veterans' march in the United States [New York City?], and enlargements/copy prints. Burns most likely created the copy prints in this series. Some of these prints have Burns' original notations.
Arrangement
Series I, arranged by original inventory. Series II, arranged alphabetically by subject.
The photographic prints contain four numbers separated by colons. The first number refers to the collection number, the second to the box number, the third to the folder number, and the fourth to the individual print. For example, the first print in this collection is labeled 184:1:1:1.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Missing Title
I, Photographers inventory
II, Subject Files
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Paul Burns Papers, ALBA 184.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, British.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Black-and-white photographs.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Fisher, Harry, 1911-2003; Bjoze, Jack; Roach, Douglas.; Shirai, Jakku, d. 1937.; Law, Oliver.; Nelson, Steve, 1903-1993; Copic, Vladimir, 1891-1939; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Thaelmann Battalion; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. British Battalion; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Tom Mooney Company
- Series I: Photographer's Inventory
  - Wall Newspaper, Jarama Front, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Second section, 1st Infantry Company, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Grave of a member of the British Saklatvala Battalion, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lincoln Battalion members Juan Castro, Captain Van Der Bergh, Martin Hourihan, Jarama (contains print and negative), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fred Copeman of the British Saklatvala Battalion, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - International Brigade, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Martin Hourihan, Joseph Whelan, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Vladimir Copic, Hans Klaus, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Peter Kerrigan and Fred Copeman, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Thalmann Battalion concert, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Yugoslav volunteers, Captain Chapiev, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Front lines barber shop, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - George Meredith, Fred Copeman, Lieutenant Cummings, Lieutenant Patterson, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - American, Irish, and Spanish, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cuban section of Lincoln Battalion infantry, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Tom Mooney Machine Gun Company, Jarama (includes print and negative), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Brigade Commander Copic with Yugoslav volunteers, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Spanish soldiers and scouts, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Daniel Sullivan, Melvin Offsink, Max Krauthamer, Reuben Scheidernam, Jack Shirai, Will Hayes, Joseph Rosenstein, James Forrestal, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lincoln Battalion, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Artemio Luna, Juan Santiago, Jack Shirai, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Charles O’Flaherty, John Reagan, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Americans, Canadians, Irish and Germans, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Tom Mooney Machine Gun Company, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Yugoslav volunteers, Jarama Valley, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Lincoln Infantry, Jarama (includes print and negative), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Fred Lutz, Wall Newspaper, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Wall Newspaper, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Mike Dempsey and Lincoln Battalion Staff, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Milton Goldstein in make believe radio station, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Greeks in Lincoln Battalion, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Mixed group waiting for the water truck, Jarama (includes print and negative), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Water carriers, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Water carriers below the front line, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Lincoln men relaxing behind the front line, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Converted shell hole serves as a barber shop, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Lincoln men relaxing in Morate de Tajuana, man on mule is John Tisa, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Dug outs and dug ins behind the front, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Lincoln Battalion parading in Alcala De Henares, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Members of the Yugoslav Battalion, Captain Chapiev, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Dr. William Pike, American in front of bullet punctured ambulance, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Lincoln men resting between shifts, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - American first aid station. Jack Bjoze of New York gets a bandage, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Command Post Tom Mooney Machine Gun Company, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Lincoln Battalion communication trench, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Lincoln men using portable bath house behind the front, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Tom Mooney Machine Gun Headquarters, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Lincoln men picking up rations to carry up to the front, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Cook house scene, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - International Brigade men on arrival at Alcala De Henares for a three day rest, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Cook house staff loading rations for delivery to front, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Steve Troxell from Youngstown Ohio and Bernardo Humanes, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - This image was eliminated because it is the personal property of the widow of a Lincoln Man and is a Tarjeta Postal which could not be duplicated, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Seamen from all over the world who shipped out of American Ports. Man holding up newspaper is Barney Spalding from Philadelphia, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Winter scene, somewhere in Spain, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Wall Newspaper at the front and constant readers, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Members of the Lincoln Battalion forming up for the memorial parade at Alcala De Henares, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Concert behind front lines by members of the German Thalmann Brigade, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Steve Nelson, Harry Fisher, Douglas Roach, Brunete, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Mixed group of Lincolns, Spaniards, Cubans and Puerto Ricans, Jarama, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - [Negative which matches print #27. It has been moved to folder #27], undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Court martial Proceedings outside brigade headquarters, Jarama, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Series II: Subject Files
  - Copy Prints, undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Copy Prints from Books, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Douglas Roach and John Perrone, Jul 13, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Group Shot: Front – Left to Right: Peter O’Conner – Waterford, Michael Kelly, Galway, Dublin Hayes, Dublin (?) – Reagan (?) Carks Bank (?) England (London) Back – Burns, Baston (?) Pehil, NYC, John Povero (?) Waterford Ireland – Coleman, Dublin., undated (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Group Shot: Unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Veterans March, undated (Box 1, Folder 69)